<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
  <style type="text/css">
    @media print {
      body { }
      p.img { text-align: center; page-break-inside: avoid }
      img.CC { display: inline }
    }
    @media screen {
      body { max-width: 800px; margin: auto }
      p.img { text-align: center }
      img.CC { display: inline }
    }
    p.date {
      font-size: smaller;
      margin: 0;
    }
    p.versionHistory {
      color: gray
    }
    p.versionHistory a {
      color: gray
    }
    p.ref {
      text-indent: -2em;
      padding-left: 2em;
    }
    p.fig {
      text-align: left;
    }
    p.fig img, img.plot {
      box-shadow: 10px 10px 20px;
      margin-top: 10px;
      margin-bottom: 20px;      
    }
  </style>

</head>
<body>
  <h1>Luminance Masks in R Graphics</h1>
  <p>
    <span style="font-style: italic">by Paul Murrell</span>
    <a href="http://orcid.org"><img alt="" src="https://www.stat.auckland.ac.nz/~paul/ORCID/ORCiD.png" style="width: 16px; height: 16px; vertical-align: middle" /></a> <span style="font-family: mono; font-size: small"><a href="http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3224-8858">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3224-8858</a></span>
  </p>
  <p class="date">
    Version 1:  
    <rcode echo="FALSE" results="asis"><![CDATA[
cat(format(Sys.Date(), "%A %d %B %Y"))
    ]]></rcode>
  </p>

  <rcode id="init" echo="FALSE" message="FALSE" results="hide"><![CDATA[
opts_chunk$set(comment=" ", tidy=FALSE, 
               dev="png", ## dev="svg",
               dpi=96)
options(width=100)
## For wonky desktop set up
options(bitmapType="cairo")
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode echo="FALSE" message="FALSE"><![CDATA[
    library(grid)
  ]]></rcode>

  <hr/>
  <p>
    <a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><img class="CC"
    alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
    src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/88x31.png"/></a><br/><span
    xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
    property="dct:title">This document</span>
    by <span xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#"
    property="cc:attributionName">Paul
    Murrell</span> is licensed under a <a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative
    Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</a>.
  </p>
  <hr/>
  <p>
    This document describes an extension of the support for 
    masks in the R graphics to allow luminance masks. 
  </p>
  <p>
    These features are available in the development version of R 
    (to become 4.2.0).
  </p>
  <p>
    R users wanting to try out the new graphics features should start with
    the <a href="#api"/> Section, which provides a quick introduction
    to the new R-level interface.
  </p>
  <p>
    Maintainers of R packages that provide R graphics devices should
    read the <a href="#device"/> Section, which provides a description of the
    required changes to R graphics devices. 
  </p>
  <p>
    Luminance masks are currently only available on the
    <code>pdf()</code> graphics device.
    Graphics devices from other R packages should
    be reinstalled and will not produce the correct output until
    (or unless)
    the package maintainer adds support.
  </p>

  <toc/>

  <h2><a name="intro">Introduction</a></h2>

  <p>
    Changes to the graphics engine in R 4.1.0 added support for
    gradient and pattern fills, clipping paths, and masks 
    (<a href="#murrell-definitions-2020"/>).  
    The following example demonstrates the use of a mask.
  </p>
  <p>
    The drawing we will use the mask on is a simple piece of text
    on a coloured background.  We will refer to this as the "test image".
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
library(colorspace)
bg <- rectGrob(gp=gpar(col=NA, fill=4))
tg <- textGrob("masked", 
               gp=gpar(cex=3, fontface="bold", col=darken(4, .7))) 
testGrob <- gTree(children=gList(bg, tg))
grid.group(testGrob)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The mask is a circle with a semitransparent fill.
    A thick green line is drawn first so that we can
    see that the circle is semitransparent.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
alphaCircle <- circleGrob(gp=gpar(col=NA, fill=rgb(0,0,0,.5)))
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
grid.draw(alphaCircle)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The following code enforces a mask based on the semitransparent circle
    and then draws the test image.
    This mask is called an "alpha" mask because the semitransparency
    (alpha channel) of the mask dictates how the test image gets drawn.
    In this case, where the circle overlaps the test image,
    the test image becomes semitransparent because the circle is
    semitransparent.  Outside of the mask, nothing
    is drawn.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
pushViewport(viewport(mask=alphaCircle))
grid.group(testGrob)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The following code shows a slightly more complex mask.  
    This
    time the mask is a circle with a semitransparent fill and 
    a thick opaque border.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
solidCircle <- circleGrob(gp=gpar(col="black", lwd=20, fill=rgb(0,0,0,.5)))
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
grid.draw(solidCircle)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The following code enforces this more complex mask and then draws the 
    test image again.
    This is also an alpha mask so the semitransparency of the
    mask is transferred to the test image.
    The result is similar to the previous example, 
    except that, where the opaque circle border
    overlaps the test image, the test image is drawn opaque.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
pushViewport(viewport(mask=solidCircle))
grid.group(testGrob)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    Some graphics languages, like Adobe Portable Document Format (PDF) 
    (<a href="#PDF"/>) 
    and Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) (<a href="#CSS"/>) allow 
    for another type of mask called a "luminance" mask.
    In a luminance mask, the luminance (greyscale values) of the mask,
    rather than the semitransparency of the mask,
    dictates how other shapes will be drawn.
  </p>
  <p>
    This document describes the extension of mask support in R graphics
    to allow for luminance masks as well as alpha masks.
  </p>

  <h2><a name="api">User API</a></h2>
  <p>
    Since the release of R version 4.1.0, the <code>viewport()</code> function
    in the 'grid' package has had a <code>mask</code> argument.
    If the value of that argument is a 'grid' grob, that grob
    is used as the basis for an alpha mask.
  </p>
  <p>
    A new function, <code>as.mask()</code>, has been added so that
    we can associate a grob with a mask type.  For example, the
    following code defines a luminance mask that is based
    on a circle with a grey fill and a thick white border.
  </p>
  <rcode><![CDATA[
luminanceCircle <- circleGrob(gp=gpar(col="white", lwd=20, fill="grey50"))
luminanceMask <- as.mask(luminanceCircle, type="luminance")
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The following code draws the circle that we are using as a luminance
    mask.  This is quite different from the previous alpha mask
    because it is completely opaque;  the green line drawn in the background
    is <em>not</em> visible beneath the mask.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
grid.draw(luminanceCircle)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The <code>mask</code> argument to <code>viewport()</code> will now
    accept an object created with <code>as.mask()</code> as well as
    a simple grob.  
    The following code pushes a viewport to enforce the luminance mask 
    and then draws the test image that we have used before.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.keep="none" results="hide"><![CDATA[
pdf("luminance-mask.pdf", width=2, height=1)
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
pushViewport(viewport(mask=luminanceMask))
grid.group(testGrob)
dev.off()
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode echo="FALSE"><![CDATA[
system("pdftoppm -png -rx 96 -ry 96 luminance-mask.pdf > luminance-mask.png")
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    <img class="plot" src="luminance-mask.png"/>
  </p>
  <p>
    The result is the same as the last alpha mask example,
    but in this case the semitransparency of the text has been derived
    from the greyscale values of the luminance mask.  Where the mask
    is white, the test image is drawn opaque and, where the mask is grey,
    the test image is drawn semitransparent.
  </p>
  <p>
    The following code produces the same result as the first alpha
    mask example, but using a luminance mask instead.
    This time the mask is just a grey circle (with no border).
  </p>
  <rcode><![CDATA[
luminanceCircle <- circleGrob(gp=gpar(col=NA, fill="grey50"))
luminanceMask <- as.mask(luminanceCircle, type="luminance")
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
grid.draw(luminanceCircle)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The following code pushes a viewport to enforce the luminance mask 
    and then draws the test image again.  
    The result is the same as the first alpha mask example, but this
    time the test image is semitransparent where it overlaps with the circle
    because the circle is filled with grey.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.keep="none" results="hide"><![CDATA[
pdf("luminance-mask-2.pdf", width=2, height=1)
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
pushViewport(viewport(mask=luminanceMask))
grid.group(testGrob)
dev.off()
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode echo="FALSE"><![CDATA[
system("pdftoppm -png -rx 96 -ry 96 luminance-mask-2.pdf > luminance-mask-2.png")
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    <img class="plot" src="luminance-mask-2.png"/>
  </p>

  <h2><a name="device">Device API</a></h2>
  <p>
    There is no change required to graphics devices as a result of this 
    change.  However, devices can now inspect the type of a mask
    to check whether it is an alpha mask or a luminance mask.
  </p>
  <p>
    The first argument to <code>dev-&gt;setMask()</code> is an R function
    that defines the mask
    (as before), but this function now has a <code>"type"</code> 
    attribute.
    The new <code>R_GE_maskType()</code> function, given the R function
    that is passed in to <code>dev-&gt;setMask()</code>,
    returns an integer representing the 
    type of mask.  Integer constants
    <code>R_GE_alphaMask</code> and <code>R_GE_luminanceMask</code>
    are provided for devices
    to switch between the two types of mask.
  </p>

  <h2><a name="discussion">Discussion</a></h2>
  <p>
    It is now possible to work with luminance masks 
    (as well as alpha masks) in R graphics.  As with other 
    recent expansions of the R graphics capabilities,
    this hopefully allows users to produce images purely
    in code rather than having to resort to manual, post-hoc editing
    of an R plot in other GUI software.
  </p>
  <p>
    One reason why luminance masks in particular
    are useful is because it is sometimes
    simpler to define a luminance mask than it is to define
    an alpha mask.  For example, the following code defines a
    luminance mask that consists of a circle filled in white
    with a thick grey border and a thick, vertical, grey
    line running through its centre.
  </p>
  <rcode><![CDATA[
luminanceGrob <- gTree(children=gList(circleGrob(),
                                      segmentsGrob(.5, 0, .5, 1)),
                       gp=gpar(col="grey50", lwd=20, fill="white"))
luminanceMask <- as.mask(luminanceGrob, type="luminance")    
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
grid.draw(luminanceGrob)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    When we enforce this mask it 
    produces semitransparency in all grey regions and 
    opacity in all white regions, as shown below.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.keep="none" results="hide"><![CDATA[
pdf("luminance-mask-3.pdf", width=2, height=1)
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
pushViewport(viewport(mask=luminanceMask))
grid.group(testGrob)
dev.off()
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode echo="FALSE"><![CDATA[
system("pdftoppm -png -rx 96 -ry 96 luminance-mask-3.pdf > luminance-mask-3.png")
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    <img class="plot" src="luminance-mask-3.png"/>
  </p>
  <p>
    Producing an equivalent alpha mask is difficult.
    For example, in the naive approach below, we define a mask based on 
    an opaque filled circle with a semitransparent 
    thick border and a semitransparent vertical line on top.
    Note that the important feature in an alpha mask is the
    mask transparency;  an opaque red is equivalent to an opaque black
    (we use red here because it makes it easier to see the semitransparent
    border an line drawn on top).
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
circle <- circleGrob(gp=gpar(col=NA, fill=2))
border <- circleGrob(gp=gpar(col=rgb(0,0,0,.5), lwd=20, fill=NA))
line <- segmentsGrob(.5, 0, .5, 1, gp=gpar(col=rgb(0,0,0,.5), lwd=20))
alphaMask <- gTree(children=gList(circle, border, line))
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
grid.draw(alphaMask)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    If we use this mask on the test image, we get a very different result
    compared to the previous luminance mask.
    This alpha mask is opaque wherever the red circle is drawn and so the
    test image is opaque wherever the red circle is drawn.
    Only the parts of the semitransparent border that stick out past
    the red circle result in a semitransparent test image.
    In essence, it is difficult to <em>reduce</em> the transparency 
    of regions of the mask by <em>adding</em> more drawing.    
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
pushViewport(viewport(mask=alphaMask))
grid.group(testGrob)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    Another general benefit of adding luminance masks, and other
    sophisticated graphics features, is that this
    expands the "vocabulary" of R graphics.  It becomes possible to
    express new graphical results and it becomes possible to think
    about new solutions to graphical problems.
  </p>
  <p>
    For example, we have just seen that it is not straightforward to
    produce an alpha mask that corresponds to a relatively straightforward
    luminance mask.  Because luminance masks are only available on
    the <code>pdf()</code> device, this means that 
    we cannot use a luminance mask
    to produce the same result on a Cairo-based device.
    However, on Cairo-based devices, we can use compositing operators
    that are not available on the <code>pdf()</code> device, e.g.,
    the <code>"source"</code> operator
    (see <a href="#murrell-groups-2021"/>). 
  </p>
  <p>
    The following code demonstrates that we can produce an alpha
    mask that is equivalent to the luminance mask if we combine the circle,
    the semitransparent thick border, and the semitransparent vertical line
    using the <code>"source"</code> operator.  Using the <code>"source"</code>
    operator means that, for example, when we add the border to the
    circle, the border <em>replaces</em> the circle wherever the two
    overlap.  In this way, we can replace the opaque circle with the
    semitransparent border (where they overlap) and we can replace the 
    opaque circle with the vertical line in the same way.
  </p>
  <rcode><![CDATA[
alphaMask <- groupGrob(line, "source", 
                       groupGrob(border, "source", circle))
  ]]></rcode>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
grid.draw(alphaMask)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    The result from using this alpha mask is the same as the result
    that we saw from using the luminance mask.
  </p>
  <rcode fig.width="2" fig.height="1"><![CDATA[
grid.segments(gp=gpar(col=3, lwd=20))
pushViewport(viewport(mask=alphaMask))
grid.group(testGrob)
  ]]></rcode>
  <p>
    That is not a demonstration of using a luminance mask to solve
    a problem (in fact, a luminance mask created the problem - how 
    to produce the same effect as a luminance mask on a graphics 
    device that does not support luminance masks!).
    However, it is a demonstration of the general idea that 
    having access to more sophisticated graphical tools makes it
    possible for us to think of new solutions to problems.
  </p>

  <h3>Limitations</h3>
  <p>
    The major limitation of luminance masks in R graphics
    is that they are only 
    supported on the <code>pdf()</code> graphics device so far.
    Graphics devices based on the Cairo graphics library 
    (<a href="#cairo"/>)
    will ignore luminance masks (with a warning).
    Other graphics devices within 'grDevices' will just silently
    ignore masks altogether.
    The 'ragg' device (<a href="#pkg:ragg"/>) has added support for alpha masks
    so it will hopefully also be able to support luminance masks.
  </p>
  <p>
    Another limitation is that luminance masks are only available
    via the 'grid' package.  There is no user interface for the
    'graphics' package.  The 'gridGraphics' package 
    (<a href="#pkg:gridGraphics"/>) 
    provides a workaround, allowing 'graphics' output to be converted
    to 'grid' output. 
  </p>
  <p>
    In time, it may be that the 'ggplot2'
    package (<a href="#pkg:ggplot2"/>) provides a way to make use of masks;
    in the meantime, the 'gggrid' package (<a href="#pkg:gggrid"/>) provides
    a simple interface for adding 'grid' output to a 'ggplot2' plot.
  </p>

  <h2><a name="requirements">Technical requirements</a></h2>
  <p>
    The examples and discussion in this report relate to 
    the development version of R (specifically revision 81125),
    which will probably become R version 4.2.0.
  </p>
  <p>
    This report was generated within a Docker container
    (see <a href="#Resources">Resources</a> section below).
  </p>

  <h2><a name="Resources">Resources</a></h2>
  <ul>
    <li>
      The <a href="masks.cml">raw source file</a> for this
      report, a <a href="masks.xml">valid XML</a>
      transformation of the source file, a <a
      href="masks.Rhtml">'knitr' document</a> generated from
      the XML file, 
      two <a href="toc.R">R</a> <a href="bib.R">files</a> and
      the <a href="masks.bib">bibtex file</a>
      that are used to generate the table of contents and reference sections,
      two <a href="common.xsl">XSL</a> <a
      href="knitr.xsl">files</a> and an 
      <a href="knit.R">R file</a> that are used to transform the XML to
      the 'knitr' document, and a <a href="Makefile">Makefile</a> that
      contains code for the other transformations and coordinates
      everything.  
      These materials are also available
      on <a href="https://github.com/pmur002/masks-report/releases/tag/v1">github</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      This report was generated within a 
      <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> container.
      The Docker command to build the report is included in the Makefile above.
      The Docker image for the container is available from
      <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/pmur002/masks-report/">Docker Hub</a>;
      alternatively, the image can be rebuilt from its 
      <a href="Dockerfile">Dockerfile</a>.
    </li>
  </ul>

  <h2>How to cite this report</h2>
  <p>
    Murrell, P. (2021). "Luminance Masks in R Graphics" 
    Technical Report 2021-0?, Department of Statistics, The University of Auckland. 
    Version 1.
    [ <a href="how-to-cite.bib">bib</a> |
      <a href="http://dx.doi.org/">DOI</a> | 
      <a href="https://stattech.blogs.auckland.ac.nz/">http</a> ]
  </p>

  <h2><a name="references">References</a></h2>
  <ul style="list-style-type: none">
    <li>
      <a name="R"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="murrell-definitions-2020"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="murrell-groups-2021"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="PDF"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="CSS"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="cairo"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="pkg:ragg"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="pkg:gridGraphics"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="pkg:ggplot2"/>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a name="pkg:gggrid"/>
    </li>
  </ul>

  <hr/>
  <p>
    <a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><img class="CC"
    alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
    src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/88x31.png"/></a><br/><span
    xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
    property="dct:title">This document</span>
    by <span xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#"
    property="cc:attributionName">Paul
    Murrell</span> is licensed under a <a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative
    Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</a>.
  </p>

</body>
</html>
